Hi everybody and welcome to lesson six
where we're going to continue looking at training convolutional neural networks for a computer vision and
so we last looked at this so lesson before last and
specifically we were looking at how to train an image classifier to pick out breeds of
pet one of 37 breeds of pet
and we've gotten as far as training him at all, but
We also had to look and figure out what loss function was actually being used
So in this model, and so we talked about cross-entropy loss
Which is actually a really important concept and some of the things we're talking about today
Depend a bit on you understanding this concept
so if you
Were at all unsure about where we got to with that go back and have another look have a look at the questionnaire
Particular and make sure that you're comfortable with cross-entropy loss
If you're not you may want to go back to the zero for M
Nist basics notebook and remind yourself about m nest loss because it's very very similar. That's what we built on the build-up cross-entropy loss
So having trained our model and the next thing we're going to do is look at model interpretation, there's not much point
having a model if you don't see what it's doing and
one thing we can do is use a
confusion matrix
Which in this case is not terribly helpful
There's a kind of a few too many and it's not too bad. We can kind of see some colored areas
And so this diagonal here all the ones that are classified correctly. So for Persians, there were 31
Asif eiders Persians
But we can see there's some bigger numbers here like a Siam
Yz6 were misclassified. They actually continued considered a Behrman
but for when you've got a lot of
Classes like this it might be better instead to use. I'm the most confused
method and that tells you the
combinations
Which it got wrong the most often in other words which numbers are the biggest so actually here's the biggest 110 and
that's confusing an American Pitbull Terrier or a
Staffordshire Bull Terrier that's happened ten times and
A rag doll is getting confused with a Burman eight times. And so I'm not a
dog or cat
expert and so I don't know what this stuff means so I looked it up on the internet and
I found that American Pit Bull Terriers and Staffordshire. Bull. Terriers are almost identical
That I think they sometimes have a slightly different colored nose. I remember correctly and
rag dolls, and Berman's are types of cat that are
so similar to each other that there's whole long threads on cat lava forums about Isis a rag doll or as is a Behrman and
Experts disagreeing with each other. So no surprise that
These things are getting confused. So when you see your model making
sensible
mistakes the kind of mistakes that humans make that's a pretty good sign that
It's picking up the right kind of stuff and that there kinds of errors you're getting also might be pretty tricky to fix
But you know, let's see if we can make it better
And one way to try and make it better is to
Improve our loading rate. Why would we want her to prove the learning rate?
Well one thing we'd like to do is to try to train it faster
Get more done in less and so one way to do that would be to call
Our fine-tuned method with a higher learning rate the last time we used
The default, which I think is
Nectar
Point one it's going to jump further each time. So remember the learning rate if you've forgotten this have a look again at notebook for
That's the thing. We multiply the gradients by to decide. How far to step
And unfortunately when we use this higher learning rate the error rate goes from 0.08 three epochs
Point eight three, so we're getting the vast majority of them wrong now, so that's not a good sign
So why did that happen? But what happened?
It's rather than this gradual move towards the minimum
We had this thing where we step too far and we get further further away
So, what do you see this happening which locks in practice like this your error are getting worse right from the start
That's a sign. Your learning rate is too high. So we need to find something just right
not too small that we take tiny jumps and it takes forever and not too big that we
you know either get worse and worse or
We just jump backwards and forwards quite slowly
so to find a good learning rate we can use something that
The researcher Leslie Smith came up with called the learning rate finder and the learning rate finder is pretty simple all we do
Remember when we do stochastic gradient descent. We look at one mini batch at a time
There are a few images in this case at a time
find the gradient for that set of images for the mini batch and
Jump you step our weights based on the learning rate and the gradient
Well what Leslie Smith said was ok
let's do the very first mini batch at a really really low learning rate like 10 to the minus 7 and
then let's
increase
by a little bit there like maybe 25 percent higher and
Through another step and then 25 percent higher and to another step
So these are not epochs. These are just a sink or a similar mini batch and then we can plot on this chart here
Ok at 10 to the minus 7. What was the loss and at 25 percent higher than that?
What was the loss and the 25 percent higher than that? What was the loss and so not surprisingly?
If you do that at the low learning rates, the loss doesn't really come down because the learning rate is so small
that these steps a
tiny tiny tiny
And then gradually
we get to the point where they're big enough to make a difference and the law starts coming down because we've plotted here the
learning rate
Against the loss. All right
So here the loss is coming down as we continue to increase the learning rate the loss comes down
until we get to a point where our learning rates too high and so
It flattens out and then well, it's getting worse again. So here's the point above like
0.1
We're we're in this territory
So what we really want is somewhere around here
Where it's kind of nice and steep
So you can actually ask it the learning rate finders were used LR find to get this plot we can
We can get back from at the minimum and steep and so steep is where was it steepest?
but the steepest point was by v-neck three and
the
Minimum point divided by ten. That's quite a good rule of thumb is one a neg - Oh somewhere around this range
Might be pretty good
So each time you run it you'll get different values a different time we ran it
We thought that maybe very Enix really would be good. So we picked that
And you'll notice the learning rate finder is a logarithmic scale. We're careful of interpreting that
so we can now rerun the learning rate finder setting the learning rate to a
number we picked from the learning root finder which in this case was 3 n X 3 and
We can see now. That's looking good. Right? We've got an eight point three percent error rate
after three epochs
So this idea of the learning rate finder is very straightforward. I can describe it to you in a couple of sentences
It doesn't require any complex math and yet it was only invented in
Which is super interesting, right? It just shows that there's so many
Interesting things first, you'll to learn and discover. I think part of the reason perhaps for this it took a while is that
You know engineers kind of love
using lots and lots of computers
so before the learning rate finder came along people would like run lots of
Experiments on big clusters to find out which learning rate was the best rather than just doing a batch at a time
and I think partly also the idea of having a thing where a human is in the loop where we look at something and make
A decision is also kind of unfashionable a lot of folks in research and Industry love things which are fully automated
But anyway, it's great. We now have this tool because it makes our life easier and
Faster I
certainly the first library to have this and I don't know if it's still the only one to have it built in at least to
the basic the base library
So now we've got a good learning rate
how do we
Find you in the weights. So so far. We've just been running this fine-tuned method without thinking much about what it's actually doing
That we did mention
in chapter 1
lesson 1 briefly
Basically, what's happening with a fine tune? What is transfer learning doing?
And before we look at that, let's take a question
Is the learning rate plot in LR find plotted against one single mini batch
No, it's not it's just it's actually just the standard kind of walking through
Walking through the data loader, so just getting the usual
mini batches of the shuffled data and so it's kind of just trip normal training and the only thing that's being different is that we're
Increasing the learning rate a little bit after each mini batch, and I'm keeping track of it
Along with that is is the network reset to the initial status after each trial
No, certainly not we actually want to see how it our learns we want to see it improving
So we don't reset it to its initial state state until we're done
so at the end of it we go back to the random weights we started with or whatever the weights were at the time we
ran this
So what we're seeing here is is something that's actually the the actual learning that's happening as we at the same time increase
the learning rate
Why would an ideal learning rate found with a single mini-batch at the start of training keep being a good learning rate even after several
epochs and further loss reductions
Okay question it absolutely wouldn't so let's look at that too. Shall we?
And
Don't ask one more
That's an important point. So Oscars bonus is very important for the learning rate finder why use the steepest and not the minimum?
We certainly don't want the minimum because the minimum is the point at which it's not learning anymore, right?
So so the fist flat section at the bottom here means in this mini vector didn't get better
So we want the steepest because that's the mini-batch where it got the most improved and that's what we want
We want the weights to be moving as fast as possible
As a rule of thumb though, we do find that the minimum divided by ten works pretty well
that's Sylvia's favorite approach and he's
Generally pretty spot-on with that. So that's why we actually print out those two things
LR mean is actually the minimum divided by 10 and steepest point is suggest the steepest point
Great but questions Oh
So remind ourselves what transfer learning does but with transfer learning remember what our neural network is it's a bunch of
linear models, basically with
Functions between them
Our activation functions are generally Relius rectified linear units any of this is fuzzy have a look at
The zero for notebook again to remind yourself
And
So each of those linear layers has a bunch of parameters to the whole neural network has a bunch of parameters and so
After we train a neural network on
something like imagenet
We have a whole bunch of parameters that aren't random anymore. They're actually useful for something
And we've also seen that the early layers
Seem to learn about fairly general ideas
Like gradients and edges and the later layers learn about more sophisticated ideas
Like what our eyes look like or what does fur look like or what does text look like?
So with transfer learning we take a model. So in other words a set of parameters
Which has already been trained on something like image net
we throw away the very last layer because the very last layer is the bit that
Specifically says which one of those in the case of image net 1000 categories?
Is this an image in so we throw that away and we replace it with random weights
Sometimes with more than one layer of random weights and then we train that
Now
Yes, Oh I just wanted to make a comment and that's that I think the learning rate finder and
I think after you learn about it the idea
Almost seems kind of so simple or approximate that it's like wait
This shouldn't work like or you know, shouldn't you have to do something more more?
complicated or more precise that it's like I just want to highlight that this is a very surprising result that some kind of the
Such as simple approximate method would be so helpful
Yeah, I would particularly say it's surprising to people who are not practitioners or who have not been practitioners for long
I've noticed that a lot of my students at
USF
Have a tendency to kind of jump in to try to doing something very complex where they account for every possible imperfection from the start
And it's very rare that that's necessary. So one of the cool things about this is a good example of
Trying the easiest thing first and seeing how well it work. And this was a very big innovation when it came out
that I think it's kind of easy to take for granted now, but this was
super super helpful when it was
It was super helpful, and it was also nearly entirely ignored
none of the research community cared about it and it wasn't until first AI I think in our first course talked about it that
People's bad at noticing and we had quite a few years. In fact is still a bit the case where?
Super fancy researchers still don't know about the learning rate finder and you know
Get get beaten by
you know first lesson faster hi students on practical problems because they can pick learning rates better and they can do it without a
cluster of thousands of Buddhas
Okay, so
Transfer loading. So we've got our pre-trained Network. And so it's really important every time you hear the word pre-trained network
You're thinking a bunch of parameters, which have particular
American values and
Go with a particular architecture like ResNet 34
We've thrown away the the final layer and replace them with random numbers
and
So now we want to train to fine tune
This set of parameters for a new set of images in this case pets
um, so
Fine-tune is the method we call to do that and to see what it does we can go
burned-up fine-tune question mark and we can see the source code and
here is the
Signature of the function and so the first thing that happens is we call
freeze
so freeze is actually the method which
Makes it so only the last layers weights will get stepped by the optimizer
So the gradients are calculated just for those last layers of parameters and the step is done just for those last layer of parameters
So then we call fit
and we fit
For some number of epochs which mode if which by default is one. We don't change that very often
and
What that fit is doing is it's just fitting those randomly added weights, which makes sense, right?
They're the ones that are going to need the most work
Because at the time in which we add them they're doing
Nothing at all. They're just random. So that's why we spend one a park trying to make them better
After you've done that you now have a model which is much better than we started with it's not random anymore
All the layers except the last are the same as the pre train network. The last layer has been tuned for this new data set
Sort of the closer you get to the right answer
As you can kind of see in this picture
The smaller the steps you want to create as this area the smaller steps you want to take?
Generally speaking
so the next thing we do is we divide our learning rate by 2 and
Then we unfreeze
so that means we make it so that all the parameters can now be stepped and
all of them will have gradients calculated and then we fit for some more epochs and this is something we have to
the pass to the method
Now gotta train the whole network so if we
Want to we can kind of do this by hand, right and actually CNN Lerner. We're all by default
freeze
the model
For us freeze the parameters for us. So we actually don't have to call freeze
So if we just create a loaner and then fit for a while
This is three epochs of training just the last layer
And so then we can just manually do it ourselves unfreeze. And so now at this point
As the question earlier suggested. Maybe this is not the right learning rate anymore so we can run LR find again
And this time you don't see the same shape
You don't see this rapid drop because it's much harder to train a model. That's already pretty good
So instead you just see a very gentle little gradient
So generally here
what we do is we kind of try to find the bit where it starts to get worse again and go about which is about
Here and go about ten let you know a multiple of ten less than that
So about one in neg five, I would guess which yep, that's what we picked. So then after unfreezing
Finding a new learning rate and then we can do a bunch more
and so here we are we are getting down to
five point nine percent error, which is okay, but there's um, there's better we can do and
The reason we can do better is that at this point here? We're training the whole
Model at a one Enoch five. So ten to the minus five learning rate
Which doesn't really make sense because we know that the last layer is still not that great
It's only had three epochs of training from random. Um, so it probably needs more work
We know that the second last layer was probably pretty specialized to imagenet and less specialized to pet breeds
So that probably needs a lot of work
Where else the early layers but kind of gradients and edges probably don't need to be changed much at all
but what would really like is to have a small learning rate for the early layers and
a bigger learning rate for the later layers
And this is something that we developed at fast AI and recall it discriminative learning rates
and
Jason Jasinski actually
Is a guy who wrote a great paper?
That's come of these ideas are based on which is he actually showed that
different layers of the network really want to be trained at different rates, although he didn't kind of go as far as
Trying that out and seeing how it goes. It's more of a theoretical thing
So in fast AI if we want to do that we can pass to our learning rate rather than just passing a single number
We can pass a slice now a slice is a special
Built-in feature of
eyghon
It's just an object which basically can have a few different numbers in it. In this case. It's we passing at two numbers
and the way we read those
Basically what this means in faster is our learning rate is the very first
Layer, we'll have this learning rate down to the minus six
The very last layer will be ten to the minus four and the layers between the two will be kind of equal multiples
So they'll kind of be equally spaced learning rates from the start to the end
So here we can see basically doing our kind of own version of
Fine tune we create the learner. We fit with that automatically frozen version
We unfreeze
When we fit some more and so when we do that you can see this works a lot better
we're getting down to five point three five point one five point four and
Error, well, that's pretty great
One thing we'll notice here is that we did kind of overshoot a bit and it seemed like more like an epoch number eight
was better
so
Kind of back before, you know, well, actually let me explain something about fit one cycle. So fit one cycle
Is a bit different to just fit. So what fit one cycle does is it actually starts at a
Laurel learning rate
It increases it gradually for the first
One-third or so of the batches until it gets to a high learning rate
The the highest were the this is why they're called LR max
It's the highest learning rate we get to and then for the remaining two-thirds or so of the batches it gradually decreases
the learning rate
And the reason for that is just that well largely. It's kind of like empirically
Researchers have found that works the best
In fact, this was developed again by Leslie Smith the same guy that did the learning rate find her again. It was a huge
Step, you know
it really dramatically accelerated the speed at which we can train your networks and also made them much more accurate and again the
Academic community basically ignored it. In fact the
Key publication that developed this idea was not even good not even past peer review
And so the reason I mentioned this now is to say that we can't we don't really just want to go back and pick the
Model that was trained back here
Because we could probably do better because we really want to pick a model. That's got a low learning rate
But what I would generally do here as I change this twelve
To an eight because this is this is looking good and then I would re train it from scratch
I've normally had find a better result
You can plot the loss and you can see how the training and validation was moved along
and you can see here that
You know the the error rate
Was starting to get worse here
And what you'll often see is often the validation
loss will get worse a bit before the
There are red gets worse. We're not really seeing it so much in this case
But the error rate and the validation lost don't or way or they're not always kind of in lockstep
so
what we're plotting here is the loss but you actually kind of want to look to see mainly what's happening with the error rate because
that's actually the thing we care about remember the loss is just like an
approximation of what we care about that just happens to
Have a gradient that works out nicely
So, how do you make it better now we're we're already down to just
5.4 or if we'd stopped bit earlier, maybe we could get down to 5.1 or less
Era on 37 categories. That's pretty remarkable. That's a very very good
pet breed predictor
If you want to do something even better you could try creating a deeper architecture. So a deeper architecture is just literally putting more
Pairs of nonlin
function also known as a non-linearity followed by these little linear models put more pairs on to the end and
They're basically the number of these
Sets of layers you have is the number that you'll see at the end of an architecture
So there's resin at 18 resin at 34 resin at 50 so forth
Having said that you can't really pick ResNet 19 or ResNet 38
I mean you couldn't make one but
Nobody's created a pre-trained version of that for you. So you won't be able to do any fine-tuning
So like you can theoretically create any number of layers you like
But in practice
Most of the time you'll want to pick a model that has a pre trained version
So you kind of have to select from the sizes people of pre trained and there's nothing special about these sizes
They're just ones that people happen to have picked out
For the bigger models
there's more parameters and more gradients that are going to be stored on your GPU and
You will get used to the idea of seeing this
this error
Unfortunately out of memory, so that's not out of memory in your RAM. That's out of memory in your GPU
Rooter is referring to the language and the system used for your TV
So if that happens, unfortunately, you actually have to restart your notebook. So that's a kernel
restart and
Try again, and that's a really annoying thing but such as life
One thing you can do if you get an out of marry error is
After you you'll see an end learner call at this
magic incantation
2fp 16
What that does is it uses for most of the operations?
Numbers that use half as many bits as usual so they're less accurate this half precision floating point or FP 16
and
That will use less memory and on pretty much any
Nvidia card
created in
2020 or later
And some more expensive cards even created in 2019 that's often got a result in a two to three time speed up
In terms of how long it takes as well. So here if I add in to FP 16, then I will be seeing
Often much faster training and in this case
what I actually did is I switched to a resinate 50 which would normally take about twice as long and
my a per apop time has gone from 25 seconds to
26 seconds. So the fact that we used a much bigger Network and it was no slower is thanks to to AFP 16
But you'll see our Arab rate hasn't improved. It's pretty similar to what it was
And so it's important to realize that just because we increase the number of lows. It doesn't always get better
So it tends to require a bit of experimentation
To find what's going to work for you?
And of course don't forget the trick is use small models for as long as possible
I'm to do all of your
Cleaning up and testing and so forth and wait until you're all done to try some bigger models
And because they're going to take a lot longer
Okay questions, how do you know or suspect when you can quote do better?
You have to always assume you can do better
because you never know so you just have to I mean
Out of it, though is you need to do better or do you already have a good enough result to?
Handle, the actual task you're trying to do often people do spend very much time
fiddling around with their models rather than actually trying to see whether it's
Already going to be super helpful
So that as soon as you can actually try to use your model to do something practical the better
Yeah, how much can you improve it who knows I
you know go through the techniques that we're teaching this course and try them and see which ones help and unless it's a
Problem that somebody has already already tried before and written down their results, you know in a paper or a cable competition or something
There's no way to know how good can
So don't forget after you do the questionnaire
So check out the further research section
And one of the things we've asked you to do here is to read a paper
So find the learning rate find a paper and read it and see if you can
kind of connect what you read up to the things that we've learned in this lesson and
see if you can maybe even implement your own learning rate finder, you know as
Manually as as you need to and see if you can get something that you know based on reading the paper to work yourself
you can even look at the source code of faster your eyes learning rate finder, of course and
Then can you make this classifier better?
And so this is further research right? So maybe you can start doing some reading to see what else could you do?
Have a look on the forum and see what people are trying have a look on the book website
Boss website and to see what other people have achieved and what they did and play around
so we've we've got some tools in our toolbox now for you to experiment with
So that is
That is Peck reads. That is a you know a pretty tricky
Computer vision classification problem
And we kind of have seen most of the pieces of what goes into the training of it
We haven't seen how to build the actual architecture
But other than that, we've we've kind of worked our way up to understanding what's going on
So let's build from there
into another kind of
Data set one that involves multi-label classification there what's multi-label classification or maybe?
So, maybe let's look at an example
Here is a multi label data set where you can see that it's not just one label on each image, but sometimes there's three
Basicall car person. I don't actually see the car here a business being popped out
so a multi label data set is one where you still got one image per row, but you can have
0 1 2 or more labels per row
So we're going to have a think about and look at how we handle that. But first of all, let's take another question
Is dropping floating-point number precision
Switching from FP 32 to FP 16 have an impact on final
Yes, it does
Often it makes it better believe it or not
It seems like you know
They're kind of it's doing a little bit of rounding off is one way to give it drop some of that precision
And so that creates a bit more
Penis a bit more uncertainty it was you know of a stochastic nature and you know when you introduce more
Lightly random stuff into training it very often makes it a bit better
and so yeah FP 16 training often gives us a slightly better result, but I you know
I wouldn't say it's generally a big deal either way and that me it's not always better
Would you say this is a bit of a pattern and learning?
Bless us exact
Kostik way
For sure not just in deep learning but machine learning more generally
You know, there's been some interesting research looking at like matrix factorization
Techniques which if you want them to go super fast, you can lots of machines you can
randomization
And you often when you then use the results you often find you actually get better better outcomes
Just a brief blog for the fast day. I
Computational linear algebra course which talks a little bit about know about Randa
That's it really well that sounds like a fascinating course and look at that it's number-one hit here on Google's are easy to find
But by somebody called Rachel Thomas hey that's persons, but their name is here Pedro Thomas
All right
So how we going to do multi-label classification?
So let's look at a data set called Pascal which is a pretty famous data set
We look at the version that goes back to 2007 been around for a long time
and
It comes with a CSV file which we will read in CSV as comma separated values and let's take a look
Each row has a file name
One or more labels and something telling you whether it's in the validation set or not
So the list of categories in each image is a space delimited string, but doesn't have a horse person
It has a horse and a person
P D here stands for pandas pandas is
Really important library
For any kind of data processing and you'll use it all the time in machine learning and deep learning
So let's have a quick chat about it
Not a real panda. It's the name of a library
And it creates things called data frames. That's what the DF here stands for and a data frame is a table containing rows and columns
Pandas can also do some slightly more sophisticated things than that, but we'll treat it that way for now
So you can read in a data frame by saying pity for pandas pandas read CSV. Give it a file name
You've now got a data frame. You can call head to see the first few rows of it for instance
a data frame as a
Eyelock integer location
Property which you can index into as if it was an array vector, it looks just like numpy so colon means
Every row remembers row comma column and zero means zeros column and so here is the first column of the data frame
Now you can do the exact opposite so the zeroth row and every column
It's going to give us the first row and you can see the row has
Column headers and values. So it's a little bit different to numpy and
remember if there's a comma colon or a bunch of comma colons at the end of indexing in numpy or
Python or pandas whatever you can get rid of it. I think these two are exactly the same
You could do the same thing here by grabbing the column by name the first column is F name
Say DF f name you get that first column
You can create new columns. So here's a tiny little data frame. I've created from a dictionary
and
I could create a new column by for example adding two columns and you can see there it is so it's like a lot like
Num PI or PI torch. I'm except you have this idea of kind of rows and and column named columns. And so it's all about
and of tabular data
I
Find its API pretty unintuitive a lot of people do but it's fast and powerful
So it takes a while to get familiar with it
But it's worth taking a while and the creator of pandas wrote a fantastic book called Python for data analysis
Which I've read both versions and I found it fantastic. It doesn't just cover pandas
it covers other stuff as well like a Python and
Numpy and matplotlib so highly recommend this book
This is our table, so what we want to do now is construct
Data loaders that we can drain with
And we've talked about the data block API as being a great way to create data loaders
but let's use this as an opportunity to create a data data loaders or a data processor create a data block and indeed loaders for
this
And let's try to do it
like
Right from square one. So, let's see exactly what's going on with datablock?
so first of all, let's remind ourselves about what a data set and the data loader is a
Data set is an abstract idea of a class
you can create a data set data set is anything which you can index into it like so or
And you can take the length of it like so so for example the list of the lowercase letters
along with a number saying which lowercase letter it is I can index into it to get 0 comma a I
can get the length of it to get 26 and so therefore this qualifies as
A data set and in particular data sets. Normally you would expect that when you index into it you would get back at Apple
because you've got the
Independent and dependent variables not necessarily always just two things
It could be more that could be less but 2 is the most common
so once we have a
Data set we can pass it to a data loader
We can repress we can request a particular batch size
We can shuffle or not. And so there's our data loader from a
We could grab the first value from that iterator
And here is the shuffled seven is H four is e twenty is U and so forth
and so I remember a mini batch has a
Bunch of a mini batch of the independent variable and a mini batch of the dependent variable
If you want to see how the two correspond to each other you can use zip. So if I passing in this list and
Then this list so be naught and B 1 you can see what zip does in Python
Is it grabs one element from each of those in turn and gives you back the tuples of?
the corresponding elements
Since we're just passing in all of the elements of B
to this function
Python has a convenient shortcut for that which is just say star B, and so star means
Insert into this parameter lists each element of B. Just like we did here. So these are the same thing
So this is a very handy idiom that we use a lot in Python. Zip star. Something is kind of a way of like
transposing something from one
orientation to another
All right, so we've got a data set we've got a data loader
And then what about data sets?
Our data sets is an object which has a training data set and a validation set data set. So let's look at one now normally
You don't
Start with kind of an enumeration like this like with with an independent variable and a dependent variable
normally you start with
like a file name, for example
and then you you kind of calculate or compute or
transform your file name into an image by opening it and
A label by for example looking at the file name and grabbing something out of it
So for example, we could do something similar here. This is what data sets does so we could start with just the lowercase letters
So this is still a data set right because we can index into it and we can get the length of it
Although it's not giving us
tuples yet
So if we now pass that list to the data sets plus and index into it we get back the tupple and
It's actually a tuple with just one item
This is how Python shows at upper with one item as it puts it in parentheses and a comma and then nothing, okay
so in practice, what we'd really want to do is to say like, okay, we'll take this and
Do something to compute an independent variable and do something to compute the dependent variable
So here's a function we could use to compute an independent variable which is to stick an A on the end and our dependent variable
Might just be the same thing with a B on the end, but here's two functions. So
for example now we can call data sets passing an A and then we can pass in a
list of
Transformations to do and so in this case, I've just got one
Which is this function at an a on the end? So now for index into it, I don't get a anymore I get a a
If you pass multiple functions then it's going to do multiple things
I've got F 1 then F 2 a a B
That's this one. That's this one and
You'll see this is a list of lists. And the reason for that is that you can also pass
something like this a list containing F 1 a list containing F 2 and this will actually take each element of a
Pass it through this
list of functions and there's just one of them to give you a a and
Then start again and separately pass it through this list of functions
There's just one to get a B. And so this is actually kind of the main way
We build up
independent variables and dependent variables in fast AI
Is we start with something like a file name? And we pass it through two lists of functions
One of them will generally kind of open up the image for example
And the other one we're going to pass the file name example and give you a independent variable and a dependent variable. So
You can then create a data loaders object
From data sets by passing in the data sets and a batch size
And so here you can see I've got shuffled Raia etc
OB IB etc
So this is worth studying to make sure you understand what data sets and data loaders are
We don't often have to create them from scratch. We can create a data block to do it for us
Now we can see what the data block has to do. Let's see how it does it
We can start by creating an empty data block
So an empty data block is going to take our data frame. We're going to go back to looking our data frame, which remember was
This guy
And
so if we pass in
Dataframe
We can now will now find that this data block has created data sets a training and a validation data set for us
And if we look at the training set
It'll give his back an independent variable in the dependent variable and we'll see that they are
That's the same thing so this is the first row of the table what's actually shuffled so it's a random row of the table
Repeated twice
And the reason for that is by default
the data block assumes that we have two things the independent variable and the dependent or the input in the target and
By default, it just copies. It just keeps exactly whatever you gave it
To create the training set in the validation set by default
It just randomly splits the data with the 20% validation set. So that's what's happened here
so this is not much use and what we what we actually want to do if we look at X for example is grab the
F name the file name field because we want to open this image that's going to be our independent variable
and then for the
label
We're going to want
This here person cat so we can actually pass these as parameters get X and get Y
functions that return
the the bit of data that we want and
So you can create an user function in the same line of code in Python by saying lambda. So lambda R
Means create a function doesn't have a name. It's going to take a parameter called R
We don't even have to say return. It's got to return the fname
Column in this case and get why is something which is a function that takes an R and
returns the labels column
So now we can do the same thing called D block that data sets
we can grab a row from that from the training set and you can see look here it is there is
The image file name and there is the space delimited list
at labels
so here's exactly the same thing again, but done with
Functions. Okay. So now the the one line of code above has become three lines of code, but it does exactly the same thing
Okay
We don't get back the same result because the training set well, wait, why don't we get the same result
Oh, I know why big we shuffle it's randomly picking a different validation set
Because the random spit is done differently each time. So that's why we don't get the same result
one thing to note be careful of lambdas
If you want to save this data block for use later
You won't be able to python doesn't like saving things that contain lambdas
so most of the time in the book and the course
We normally use avoid lambdas for that reason because this is often very convenient to be able to save things
Now we use the word here serialization. That just means basically I mean saving something
This is not enough to
Open an image because we don't have the path
so to turn this into so rather than just using this function to grab the
F name column we should actually use path Lib to go a path slash train and then column
And then for the Y again the labels is not quite enough we actually have a split on space
But this is Python we can use any function we like and so then we won't use the same three lines of code is here
and
now we've got a path and
A list and labels, so that's looking good
So we want this path to be opened as an image
so the data block API lets you pass the blocks argument where you tell it or each of the things in your
Topple so there's two of them. What kind of block do you need where we need an image block to open an image and
Then in the past we've used a category block or categorical variables. But this time we don't have a single category
We've got multiple categories where we have to use a multi in category block. So once we do that and
Have a look we're now Heaven
500 by 375 image as our independent variable and as a dependent variable we have a
long lists of zeros and ones
The long list of zeros and ones is the labels as
a one hot encoded
vector a rank one tensor and
specifically
There will be a zero in every location
where
in the vocab where there is not that kind of object in this image and
A one in every location where there is so for this one. There's just a person
So this must be the location in the vocab where there's a person?
We have any questions
The one cutting coating is a very important concept and
We didn't have to use it before right we could just have a single
integer
Saying which one thing is it but when we've got lots of things
lots of potential labels
it's it's convenient use this one hot encoding and
It's kind of what it's actually what's going to happen with with them with the actual matrices
anyway
When we actually
Compare the
Activations of our neural network to the target. It's actually going to be comparing each one of these
Okay, so the categories as I mentioned is based on the vocab where we can grab the vocab from our data
Set subject
And then we can say okay. Let's look at the first row
And let's look at the dependent variable and let's look for where the dependent variable is one
Okay, and
and
We can have a look past those indexes
There's a vocab and get back a list of what it actually was there and again each time
I run this I'm going to get different results
We run this we're going to get different results because I called datasets again here
So it's going to give me a different train test split. And so this time it turns out that this actually a chair and
We have a question
Shouldn't the tensor be of integers why is it a tensor of floats?
Yeah, conceptually this is a tensor of integers they can only be 0 1 but we
Using a cross entropy styrol loss function
so we're going to actually need to do floating-point calculations on them that's going to be faster to just
Store them as float in the first place rather than converting backwards and forwards even though they're conceptually an int
We're not going to be doing and of int style calculations with them
Question
I mentioned that by default the
Datablock uses a random split
In the data frame though
it said here's a column saying what validation set to use and if
The data set you're given tells you what validations had to use
You should generally use it because that way you can compare your validation set results to somebody else's
So you can pass a splitter argument which again is a function and so we're going to pass it a function
That's also called splitter and the function is going to return the indexes
where it's
not valid and that's their going to be the training set and the
Indexes where it is valid that's going to be the validation set
and so the splitter argument is expected to return true lists of integers and
So if we do that
We get again the same thing, but now we're using the correct training validation sets
Another question sure
Any particular reason we don't use floating point eight. Is it just that the precision is too low
Yeah trying to train with 8-bit
Precision is super difficult
it's
It's so flat and bumpy. It's pretty difficult to get decent gradients
There but you know it's an area of research the main thing people do with 8-bit or even one bit
Data types is they take a model that's already been trained with 16-bit or 32-bit floating-point and then they kind of round it off
It's called discretizing
to create a
Kind of purely integer or even binary network, which can do inference much faster
figuring out how to train
With such low precision data is an area of active research
I suspect it's possible and I suspect I mean people have fiddled had some success
I think you know it could turn out to be super interesting
Particularly for stuff that's been done on like low powered devices that might not even have a floating-point unit
You
Right, so the last thing we need to do is to add our item transforms random resource crop we've talked about that enough
So I won't go into it
But basically that means we now are going to ensure that everything has the same shape
So that we can collate it into a data loader. So now rather than going datasets
wrote data loaders and
Display our data
And remember something goes wrong as we saw last week
You can call summary to find out exactly what's happening in your data block
So now you know, this is something really worth studying this section because data blocks are super handy
And if you haven't used fast the I who before they won't be familiar to you because no other library uses them
And so like this has really shown you how to go right back to the start and gradually build them up
So hopefully that'll make a whole lot of sense
Now we're going to need a loss function again
And to do that, let's start by just creating a learner
Let's credit resonate 18 from the data loaders object. We just created
And let's grab one batch of data
and then let's put that into our mini batch of
independent and dependent variables and then learn dot model is the thing that actually contains the
The the model itself in this case, I CNN and you can treat it as a function
And so therefore we can just pass that into it. And so if we pass
A mini batch of the independent variable to learn dot model. It will return the activations from the final layer
That is
By 20, so anytime you get a tensor back look at its shape
And in fact before you look at its shape predict what the shape should be
And then make sure that you're all right if you're not either you guessed wrong
So try to understand where you made a mistake or there's a problem with your code
And this place 64 by 20
Makes sense because we have a mini batch size at 64 and for each of those we're going to make predictions about what probability is
each of these 20 possible categories
And we have a question in your question three questions
All right is the data block API compatible with out of core data sets like desc
Yeah, the data block API can do anything you wanted to do so you're passing it
If we go back to the start
So you can create an empty one and then you can pass it anything that is
Indexable
and
Yeah, so that can be anything you you like and a pretty much anything can be made indexable
in
Python and that's something like desk is certainly indexable. So that works perfectly fine
if it's
Not indexable. Like it's a it's a network stream or something like that then um the data loaders
Datasets api's directly which we'll learn about either in this course or the next one
Yeah, anything that you can index into it certainly includes desk you can use with data blocks
Next question. Where do you put images for multi-label with that CSV table? Should they be in the same directory?
There can be any way you like
so in this case, we used a path flip object like so
and
in this case the
Fault it's going to be using but I think about this
That what's happening here is the path
is oh
It's saying dot. Okay. The reason for that is that path based path is currently set to path and for that displays things relative
well, let's
rid of that
The path we set is here, right
And so then when we said get X it's saying path slash train slash whatever right? So this is an absolute path
And so here is the exact path so you can put them anywhere you like you just have to say what the path is and
then if you want to
not get confused by having this big long prefix that we can don't want to see all the time a
Set base path to the path. You want everything to be relative to and
Then it'll just print things out in this more and more convenient manner
All right, so um, this is really important that you can do this that you can create a learner
You can grab a batch of data that you can pass it to the model is this is just plain pie torch this line here
Right. No fast AI
you can see the shape, but you can recognize why it has this shape and
So now if you have a look here
are
The 20 activations now this is not a trained model
It's a pre trained model with a random set of final layer weights
So these specific numbers don't mean anything a but it's just worth remembering. This is what activations look like and
Most importantly, they're not between 0 & 1
And if you remember from the M NIST notebook
We know how to scale things between zero and one we can pop them into the sigmoid function
so the sigmoid function is something that scales everything to be between
zero and one
So let's use that
You'll also hopefully remember from the M. Nest notebook that the M nest loss
The amnesty law function first its sigmoid and then it did torch dot where
So and then it did not mean
we're going to use exactly the same thing as the eminent last function and we're just going to do one thing which is going to
Add that log
For the same reason that we talked about
when we were looking at
softmax
we talked about why log is a
Good idea as a transformation we saw in the amnesty notebook. We didn't need it
But we're gonna train faster and more accurately if we use it because it's just more it's going to be better behaved as we've seen
So this particular function, which is it identical to M
NIST loss plus log as a specific name and it's called binary cross entropy
and
We used it for the threes vs. Sevens problem
To decide whether that column. Is it a three or not?
But because we can use broadcasting in a torch and element-wise arithmetic
This function when we pass it a whole matrix is going to be applied to every column. So is the first column?
You know what, so it'll basically do a torch dot. We're on on every column
separately and every item separately
So that's great it basically means that this binary cross-entropy function is going to be just like
Amnesties being is this the number three?
It'll be is this a dog. Is this a cat? Is this a car?
Is this a person is is the bicycle and so forth?
so this is where it's so cool in PI torch we can kind of run right one thing and
Then kind of have it expand to handle higher dimensional
tensors without doing any extra work
Um, we don't have to write this as our cells, of course
because pay torch has one and
It's called F dot binary cross-entropy
That we can just use PI torches
As we've talked about there's always a equivalent module version. So this is exactly the same thing as a module and end up ECE loss
And
These ones don't include the initial sigmoid actually
if you want to include this initial sigmoid
You need F binary cross-entropy with logits or the equivalent NNPC EU is logits loss. So PCE is binary cross-entropy
and
so those are
two functions plus two equivalent classes for
multi-label or binary problems and then the equivalent for single label like M nest and pets is
Nll loss and cross-entropy, but that's the equivalent of binary cross-entropy and binary Cross interviews logits
So these are pretty awful names. I think we can all agree
But it is what it is
So in our case we have a one hot and coded target and we want the one with
sigmoid in so the equivalent
Built-in is called
BCE with logits loss so that we can make that our loss function
We can compare the activations to our targets and we can get back a loss
And then that's what we can use to Train
And then finally before we take our break we also need a metric now previously
We've been using as a metric at accuracy or actually error rate error rate is one - accuracy
macors, he only works for
single label data sets like M nest and pets
because what it does is it takes the input which is the final layer activations and
It does our mech SWAT arc max does is it says what is the index of the largest number in those activations?
So for example for M nest, you know, maybe the largest the highest probability is seven. So this arguments would return
seven
is okay there those are my predictions and
Then it says okay is the prediction
equal to the target or not and
Then take the floating-point mean but that's what accuracy is. So arcamax only makes sense when there's a single
maximum thing you're looking for in
This case we've got multi-label
Instead we have to compare
Each activation to some threshold our default is 0.5. And so we basically say if the
Sigmoid of the activation is greater than 0.5. Let's assume that means that
Category is there and if it's not let's assume it means it's not there
and so this is going to give us a list of trues and falses for the ones that
the based on the activations it thinks are there and we can compare that to the target and
Then again take the floating point me
So we can use the default threshold of 0.5
But we don't necessarily want to use 0.5 we might want to use a different threshold
And remember we have to pass when we create a learner we have to pass to the metric the metrics argument a function
So what if we want to use a threshold other than 0.5? Well, we'd like to create a special function which is accuracy
Multi with some different threshold
And the way we do that is we use a special
Built-in in Python called partial let me show you how partial works a function called. Say. Hello
Somebody with something
Hello Jeremy where the default is hello that says hello Jeremy hey hello Jeremy come out
Hi gonna be a hi Jeremy. Let's create a special version of this function. That will be more suitable for Sylvia
It's going to use French
So we can say partial create a new function
That's based on the C. Hello function, but it's always going to set say what - Bonjour
And we'll call that F. So now F Jeremy is borrowed Jeremy and F. Silva is
Borisova, so you see we've created a new function from an existing function by fixing one of its parameters
so we can do the same thing or
Accuracy, multi. Ok, let's use a threshold of 0.2 and we can pass that to metrics
and
So let's create a CNN learner and you'll notice here
We don't actually pass a loss function and that's because fast AI is not enough to realize. Hey, you're doing a classification model
with a
a
Multi-label dependent variable so I know what loss function you probably want
so it does it for us where we can call a fine tune and
Here we have an accuracy of ninety four and a half after the first few and eventually 95.1
That's pretty good. We've got an accuracy of over 95%
Was point to a good threshold to pick who knows let's try quite one well, that's a worse accuracy
So I guess in this case we could buy a higher threshold
94 hmm. Also not good. What's the best threshold?
well
what we could do is call get Preds to get all of the predictions and all of the targets and
Then we could calculate the accuracy at some threshold
Then we could say, okay, let's grab
lots of numbers between 0.05 and point nine five and
With a list comprehension calculate the accuracy for all of those different thresholds
And plot them
Ah, looks like we want
Hold somewhere a bit about 0.5
So cool. We can just use that and it's going to give us 96 in a bit
Going to give us a better accuracy
This is a you know, something that a lot of
Irritations would be uncomfortable about I've used the validation set to pick a hyper parameter a threshold, right?
And so people might be like, oh you're overfitting
Using the validation set to pick a hyper parameter, but if you think about it, this is a very smooth curve, right?
It's not some bumpy thing where we've accidentally kind of randomly grabbed some
unexpectedly good value
When you're picking a single number from a smooth curve, you know
This is where the theory of like don't use a validation set for for how parameter tuning
Doesn't really apply
So it's always good to be practical. Right? Don't treat these things as rules but as rules of thumb
Okay, so let's take a break for five minutes and I'll see you back here in five minutes time
Hey, welcome back. Oh I want to show you something really cool image regression. So
We are not going to learn how to use a fast AI image regression application because we don't need one
now that we know how to
build stuff up with boss functions and the data block API ourselves
We can invent our own applications. So there is no
image regression
application per se
But we can do image regression really easily what do we mean by image regression
We'll remember back to a lesson I think is lesson 1 we talked about the two
basic types of
machine learning or supervised machine learning
regression and classification
Assaf ocation is when our dependent variable is a discrete category or set of categories
Aggression is when our dependent variable is a continuous number like an age or
XY coordinate or something like that?
so image regression means our independent variable is an image and our dependent variable is a
Continuum or continuous value of values and so here's what that can look like
Which is the V. We had posed data set
it has a number of things in it, but one of the things we can do is find the
midpoint of a person's face
see
So
The be we at pose data set
So the B we head post dataset hum comes from
this paper
Random forest real-time 3d face analysis. So thank you to those authors
and
We can grab it in the usual way and hard data
and we can have a look at what's in there and
we can see are there's 24 directories numbered from Norton from 1 to 24 is 1 to 3 and
Each one also has a table file. We're not going to be using the Dobbs file. I'm just the directories
So let's look at one of the directories and as you can see there's a thousand things in the first directory
So each one of these 24 directories is one different person that they photographed
and to conceive for each person there's
frame three pose frame three RGB frame four pose frame for RGB and so forth
So in each case, we've got the image which is the RGB and we've got the pose is supposed to text
So as we've seen we can grab our use get image files
To get a list of all of the files image files recursively in a path
So once we have an image filename like this one sorry like this one
We can turn it into a post bio name
By removing the last one two, three, four, five six seven letters and adding back on
Texts and
So here is a function that does that and so you can see I can pass in an image file
To image to pose and get back a pose file
right, so
Pio image create is the faster a way to create an image
At least a Pio image
It has a shape in computer vision
They're normally backwards then when we do columns by rows
But that's why it's sway around where else hi tortured numpy tensors and arrays are rows by columns. So that's
Confusing but that's just how things are. I'm afraid. Um, so here's an example of an image
When you look at the readme from the dataset website they tell you how to get the center point from
From one of the text files and it's just this function that doesn't matter. The district is what it is
they call it get Center and it will return the
XY coordinate of the center of the person's head face
So we can pass this as get Y because get why I remember is a thing that gives us back the label
Okay
so
So here's the thing right we can create a data block and
we can pass in as the independent variables block image block as usual and
then the dependent variables block we can say point block which is a tensor with two values in and
now by combining these two things this says we want to do image regression with
the dependent variable with two continuous values
To get the items you call get image files to get the Y. We'll call the gap Center function
To split it so this is important we should make sure that the
Validation set contains one or more
People that don't appear in the training set
So I'm just going to grab person number 13 just grabbed it randomly and I'll use all of those images as the validation set
because I think they did this with a
Xbox Kinect, you know video thing. So there's a lot of images that look almost identical
So if you randomly assigned them, then you would be massively overestimating how effective you are
you want to make sure that you're actually doing a good job with a
Random with a new set of people not just a new set of frames
That's why we use this and so func splitter is a splitter that takes a function
And in this case, we're using lambda to create the function
We will use data augmentation
and we were also
Normalized, so this is actually done automatically now
This case we're doing it manually. So this is going to
Subtract
the
Mean and divide by the standard deviation of the original data set that the pre trainer model used which is imagenet
So that's our data block
And so we can call data loaders to get a data Lotus passing in the path and
And we can see that looks good. Right? Here's our faces and the points
So let's like particularly for as a student don't just look at the pictures look at the actual data, so grab a batch
Put it into an X B and a yv expansion Y batch and have a look at the shapes
And make sure they make sense so why is this 64 by 1 by 2?
So it's
64 in the mini batch 64 rows and then a
The coordinates is a 1 by 2
Tensor so there's a as a single
Point with two things in it. It's like you could have like hands
Face and armpits or whatever or nose and ears and mouth
so in this case, we're just using one point and the point is represented by two values the X and the y and
Then why is this 64 by 3 by 240 by 320?
Well, there's 240 rows by 320 columns as the pixels. It's the size of the images that we're using
mini-batches
64 items now. What's the three the three is the number of channels which in this case means the number of colors?
if we open up some random grizzly bear image and
Then we go through
Each of the
elements of the first axis and
Through a show image
You can see that it's got the red
The green and the blue as the three channels
So that's how we store a three channel image
is it stored as a three by number of rows by number of columns rank three tensor and
So a mini batch of those is a rank four tensor. That's why this is that shape
So here's a row from the dependent variable, okay. There's that XY location we talked about
So we can now go ahead and create a learner
passing in our data loaders as usual passing in a pre trained architecture as usual and if
You think back you may just remember in Lesson one?
We learn about why range
Why range is where we tell
Marseille I
What range of data we expect to see in the dependent variable?
So we want to use this generally when we're doing regression though
the range of our
coordinates is between minus 1 and 1 that's how fast ai and PI torch treats coordinates the
Left hand side is minus 1 or the top is minus 1 and the bottom in the right one
No point predicting something
That's more than minus one or bigger than one is that is not in the area that we use for our coordinates ever question
Sure, just a moment
So, how is Y range work, well, it actually uses this function called sigmoid range which takes the sigmoid of X
model place by high minus low and adds low and here is what
sigmoid Range
Looks like or minus 1 to 1
it's just a sigmoid where the bottom is the lower and the top is the high and
So that way all of our activations are going to be mapped to the range from minus 1 or 1
Yes, Rachel
Can you provide images with an arbitrary number of channels as inputs
specifically more than three channels
Yeah, you can have as many channels as you like. We certainly seen images with less than three because we've been grayscale
More than three is common as well. You could have like an infrared band or like satellite images often have multi spectral
There's some kinds of medical images where there are bands that are kind of outside the visible range
Your pre-trained model will generally have three channels
The first day I do is does some tricks to use three channel pre-trained models for non three channel data
but that's the only
Tricky bit. Other than that it's just
Just a you know, it's just an axis that happens to have four things or two things or one thing instead of three things
There's nothing
special about it
Okay, we didn't specify a loss function here so we get whatever you gave us which is a MSA loss
So MSA losses mean squared error and that makes perfect sense, right?
You would expect mean squared error to be a reasonable thing to use for regression. We're just testing how close we are
To the target and then taking the square picking the me
We didn't specify any metrics and that's because main squared error is already a
Good metric like it's not it's it's it's it has nice gradient
So behaves well, but it's also the thing that we care about so we don't need a separate metric to track
Let's go ahead and use ela find
And we can pick her learning rate. So maybe about n to the minus 2
we can call fine tune and
we get a valid loss of point or
One and so that's the mean squared error. So we should take the square root but on average
We're about 0.01 off in a coordinate space that goes between minus 1 and 1. Well, that sounds super accurate
Took about 3 in a bit minutes to run
So we can always call in faster
I and we always should their results see what our results look like
And as you can see faster
I has automatically figured out how to display the combination of an
image independent variable and a point dependent variable on the left is the is the target and on the right is the prediction and
As you can see it is pretty close to perfect
The really interesting things here is we used fine tune
Even although think about it the thing we're fine-tuning imagenet isn't even an image regression model. So we're actually
fine-tuning an image as a
Vacation model that becomes something totally different an image regression model
Why does that work? So well, well because
an
Image net
Classification model must have learnt a lot
About kind of how images look what things look like and where the pieces of them are
they kind of know how to figure out what
breed of animals something is even if it's partly obscured by
borscht shorts in the shade or it's turned in different angles, you know, these are pre-trained image models are
Incredibly powerful
Judah's, you know computing
Algorithms so built into every image net pre-trained model is all this capability that it had to learn for itself
So asking it to use that capability to figure out where something it's just actually not that hard for it
And so that's why we can actually fine tune
an image net classification model to create something completely different which is a
a point
Image regression model so I find that
Incredibly cool I gotta say
So again, look at the further research after you've done the questionnaire and
Particularly, if you haven't used data frames before please play with them because we're going to be using them
more and more
at question, I'll just do the last one and
Also go back and look at the bear classifier from notebook 2 or whatever hopefully you created some other
classifier for your own data because remember we talked about how
It would be better if the bear classifier could also recognize that there's no bear at all
Or maybe there's both a grizzly bear and a black bear or a chrisley bear and a teddy bear
So if you reach trainer using model label classification, see what happens
See how well it works when there's no bears
And see whether it changes the accuracy of the single label model when you turn it into a multi label
Problem. So have a fiddle around and tell us on the forum what you find. You've got a question rachel
Is there a tutorial showing how to use pre trained models on 4-channel images also?
How can you add a channel to a normal image?
Well, so that's been how do you add a channel to an image
Know what that means? Okay, okay
I don't know. You can't like an image as an image and add a channel to a name. It is what it is
Um
I don't know if there's a tutorial
But we can certainly make sure somebody on the forum has learned how to do it. It's
It's super straightforward it much automatic
Okay
We're going to talk about
collaborative filtering
Collaborative filtering, or I'll think about on Netflix or whatever
Um, you might have watched a lot of movies at a sci-fi and have a lot of action and were made in the 70s
and
Efflux might not know anything
About the properties of movies who watched it. They might just know that their
movies with titles and IDs
But what it could absolutely see without any manual work
Is find other people that watched the same movies
That you watched
Could see what other movies
Those people watch that you haven't and it would probably find they were also
We would probably find they're also science fiction and full of action and made in the 70s
so
we can use an approach where we
Recommend things even if we don't know anything about what those things are as long as we know
Who else has?
Used or recommended things that are similar, you know the same kind, you know
Many of the same things that that you've liked or or used
Um
This Cera mean users and products. In fact in collaborative filtering sourcing products when we say items and
Items could be links you click on
Diagnosis for a patient and so forth
So there's a key idea here which is that in the underlying items and we going to be using movies in this example
There are some there are some features they may not be labeled. But there's some underlying concept of features of
Of those movies like the fact that there's a
action concept and a sci-fi concept in a 1970s
Concept now you were never actually told Netflix you like these kinds of movies
And maybe Netflix never actually added columns to their movies saying what movies are those types?
but as long as like
you know in the real world, there's this concept of sci-fi and action and movie age and
That those concepts are relevant for at least some people's
movie watching decisions
As long as this is true
Then we can actually uncover
these they're called late latent factors these things that kind of decide what
kind of movies you want to watch and their latent because nobody necessarily ever wrote them down or
Labeled them or or communicated them in any way
So let me show you what this looks like
So there's a great data set we can use court movie lens
Tens of millions of movie rankings and so a movie ranking looks like this it has a user number a
Movie number
Writing
I'm step
So we don't know anything about who user number one 960s. I don't know if that is Rachel or don't bow or somebody else. I
don't know what movie number who for two is I don't know if that's Casablanca or Lord of the Rings or
the mask
And then rating is a number between I think it was one in five a question. Sure
In traditional machine learning we perform cross validations and k-fold training to check for variance and bias trade-off
Is this common in training deep learning models as well?
So cross-validation is a technique where you
Don't just let your data set into one training set and one validation set but you basically do it five or so times
Like five training sets and like five validation sets representing different
overlapping subsets
And basically this was this used to be done a lot
Because people often used to have not enough data get a good result. And so
This way rather than kind of having
Percent that you would leave out each time. You could just leave out like ten percent each time
nowadays, it's less common that we have so little data that we need to worry about the complexity and extra time of
Lots of models it's done on kaggle a lot
It's on Kegel
every little fraction of a percent matters
But it's not yeah, it's not a deep learning thing or a machine learning thing or whatever it's just a you know
Lots of data or not very much data thing. And do you care about the last?
Decimal place of him or not. It's not something we're going to talk about certainly in this part of the course if ever
Because it's not something that comes up in practice that often as being
that important
There are two more questions
What would be some good applications of collaborative filtering outside of recommender systems
Well, I mean depends how you define recommender system if you're trying to figure out
What kind of other diagnosis might be applicable to a patient?
I guess it's kind of a recommender system or you're trying to figure out
Where somebody is going to click next or whatever. It's kind of a recommender system
But you know, really conceptually it's anything where you're trying to learn from from past behavior
where that behavior is kind of like a
thing happened to an entity
What is an approach to training using video streams ie from drone footage instead of images
Would you need to break up the footage into image frames?
In practice quite often you would because images just tend to be pretty big so videos tend to be pretty big
There's a lot of sense I mean
theoretically
the
Time could be the the fourth channel. Yeah or a fifth channel
so if it's a full color movie, you can absolutely have
Well, I guess fourth because you can have but it would be a five rank five tensor being batch by time
by color by row by column
But often that's
- computationally and -
Memory-intensive
sometimes people just
One frame at a time
Sometimes people use
us a few frames around kind of the key frame like three or five frames at a time and
Sometimes people use something quite a recurrent neural network, which we'll be seeing in the next week or two
Treated as a sequence data
Yeah, there's all kinds of tricks you can do to try and go and work with that conceptually
though
There's no reason you can't just add an additional access to your tenses and everything just work. It's just a practical issue around time and
And someone else noted that it's pretty fitting that you mentioned the movie the mask
Yes, I'm not an accident I cut masks on the brain
I'm not sure if we're allowed to like that movie anymore, though
And I've liked it when it came out. I don't know. I don't think nowadays. It's a while
Okay, so
Let's take a look so we can entire data. Ml 100k. So ml 100k is a small subset of the full set
there's another one that we can grab which is about the whole lot 25 million, but 100k is good enough for
messing around
So if you look at the readme you'll find the main table
The main table is in a file called u data so let's open it up with read CSV again
This one is actually not comma separated values. It's tab separated rather confusingly
we still use CSV and to say delimiter is a tab X slash tears tab and
there's no row at the top saying what the
columns are called so we say header is none and then pass in a
List of what the columns are called
Dot head will give us the first five rows and we mentioned just before what it looks like
It's not a
particularly
Friendly way to look at it. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
Rust a bit
And so what I've done here is I've grabbed the top
I remember having it was it. Well, I guess one two three four
Fifteen or twenty movies
based on the most popular movies and the top bunch of users who watch the most movies and
so I basically kind of
Reoriented this so for each user
I have all the movies they've watched and the rating they gave them so empty spots represent users that have not seen that movie
So this is just another way of looking at this same data
So basically what we want to do is
guess what movies we should
Tell people they might want to watch and so it's basically filling in these gaps to tell user 2:12
Do you think we would they might like movie 49 or 79 or 99 best to watch next?
So, let's assume that
We actually had
columns every movie that
represented say
how much sci-fi they are how much action they are and how old they are and maybe they're between minus 1 and 1 and
So like the liar the last Skywalker is very sci-fi
Barely action and definitely not old
And then we could do the same thing for users so we could say user 1
really like sci-fi
quite likes action and
really doesn't like old and
So now if you multiply those together and remember in PI torch and numpy you have element wise calculation
So this is going to multiply each
Corresponding item. It's not matrix multiplication. If you're a mathematician don't go there
This is element wise multiplication if we want matrix multiplication to be an @ sign
Each
element together next with your equivalent element in the other one and
Then sum them up that's going to give us a number
Which will basically tell us how much do these two correspond because remember two negatives multiplied together to get a positive
So user one
Likes exactly the kind of stuff that last guy was that the last Skywalker has in it and so we get 2.1
Multiplying things together element wise and adding them up is called the dot product
And we use it on light and it's the basis of matrix tudents a modification matrix multiplication
Aunty occasion
So make sure you know, what a dot product is it's this
so Casablanca is not at all safe a
Not much action and is certainly old
So if we do user 1 times Casablanca?
We get a negative number so we might think ok user 1 more like won't like this movie
Problem is we don't know what the latent factors are and
Even if we did, we don't know how to label a particular user or a particular movie with them
So we have to learn them
How do we learn them
Well
We can actually look
At a spreadsheet so I wrote a spreadsheet version
So we have a spreadsheet version which is basically what I did was I
Popped this
table into Excel
and then I
randomly created a
Lost countless now one two, three, four, five six, seven eight nine ten, eleven. Oh,
I
Randomly created a fifteen by five label here
These are just random numbers and I randomly created a five by fifteen table here and I basically said okay
well, let's just pretend let's just assume that every
Movie and every user has five latent factors. I don't know what they are and
Let's then do a matrix model play of
this set of factors by this set of factors and a matrix model play of a row by a column is
identical to a dot product of two vectors
So that's why I can just use matrix multiply. Now. This is just what this first cell content
So they then copied it to the whole thing. So all these numbers
there are being calculated from
the row
latent factors dot product with or
Matrix model play with the column ten factors. So in other words, I'm doing exactly this calculation
But I'm doing them with rounder numbers
And so that gives us a whole bunch
Values
right, and then what I could do is I could calculate a
loss by comparing every one of these numbers here to
Every one of these numbers here and then I could remain square error
And then I could choose stochastic gradient descent
Set of numbers in each of these two locations
And that is what collaborative filtering is
So that's actually all we need
Rather than doing it Excel and
Very the Excel version later if you're interested because we can actually do this whole thing and it works in Excel
Let's jump and do it into
I
torch
Now one thing that might just make this more fun is actually to know what the movies are and movie lens tells us in
Utah item what the movies are called
And that uses the delimiter of the pipe sign weirdly enough. So here them here are the names of each movie and
so one of the nice things about pandas is it can do
Joins
Just like SQL and so you can use the merge method to combine the ratings table and the movies table
And since they both have a column called movie by default
It will join on those and so now here we have the ratings table with actual movie names
That's going to be a bit more fun. We don't need it for modeling, but it's just going to be better for looking at stuff
So
We could use data blocks API at this point or we can just use the built in
application factory method since it's there we may as well use it so we can create a
collaborative filtering data loaders object from a data frame by passing in the ratings table
By default the user
Column is called user and ours is so fine
By default. The item column is called item and ours is not it's called title. So let's pick title and
Choose a batch size. And so if we now say show batch
here is
Of that data and the rating is called rating by default, so that worked fine, too
So here's some data
so
We need to now create our
Assume we're going to use that five numbers of factors
So the number of users is however many
Classes there are for user. And the number of movies is however many classes. There are a
title and so these are
So we don't just have a vocab now, right we've actually got a list of classes for each
Categorical variable for each set of discrete choices. So we've got a whole bunch of users
944 and a whole bunch of titles
1635 so for our
randomized
latent factor
Parameters we're going to need to create those matrices so we can just create them with random numbers. This is normally distributed random numbers
That's what rent n is and that will be n users
Okay, so 944 I n factors which is 5 that's exactly the same as this except. This is just 15
Same thing for movies
random numbers and movies buy life
okay, and so to calculate the result for some movie and
some user we have to look up the index of the movie in our movie latent factors the index of the user in our
User latent factors and then do a cross product
so in other words, we would say like, oh, okay s for this particular combination
we would have to look up that numbered user over here and
That numbered movie over here to get the two
appropriate sets of latent factors
But this is a problem because
Look up in an index is not
a linear model like remember out deep learning models really only know how to just
Multiply matrices together and two simple element-wise nonlinearities like r lu there isn't a thing called lookup in an index
Okay, how does finish this bit
um
Here's a cool thing though the lookup and an index is actually can be represented
as a matrix product
Believe it or not
So if you replace
Our indices
At vectors
Then a 100 coded vector
Times something is identical to looking up in an index and let me show you
So if we grab
If we call the one hot function that creates a as it says here
One hot encoding and we're going to one hot and code the value three
with end-users classes and so end-users
As we discussed is 944
All right, then
So if we go one hot one hot encoding the number three to end-users
One hot
Three
forget this big
array big tensor and as you can see in index 3 0 1 2 3
we have a 1 and
the size of that
Is 924
So if we then multiply that by
User factors or use effectors remember is that
Random matrix of this size
Now what's going to happen
So we're going to go zero by
The first row and so that's going to be your zeros and then we're going to 0 again
We're gonna 0 again and then we're going to find a fun to go one
right on the
3-row and so it's going to return each of them and then we'll go back to zero again
So if we do that remember at sign is matrix multiply
And compare that through user factors
Three same thing isn't that crazy? So
We're an efficient way to do it, right but matrix multiplication is a way to
Index into an array and
This is the thing that we know how to do SGD with and we know how to build models with
So it turns out that anything that we can do with indexing to array
We now have a way to optimize and we have a question. There are two questions
One how different in practice is collaborative filtering with sparse data compared to dense data
We are not doing sparse data in this course, but there's an excellent
Course are here called computational linear algebra for coders. It has a lot of information about sparse
the first day, I course a
Second question in practice. Do we tune the number of latent factors?
Absolutely we do yes
just it's just a number of
filters like we have in at any kind of a
planning model
All right, so now that we know that
The procedure of finding out which
latent set of latent factors is the right thing looking something up at an index is the same as
matrix multiplication with a 100
Though I already had it over here
We can go ahead and build a model with that
so basically if we do this for a whole for a few more indices at once then we have a matrix of one hot and
Coded vectors. So the whole thing is just one big
matrix multiplication
Now the thing is as I said, this is a pretty inefficient way to
Do an index lookup so there is a computational shortcut
Which is called an embedding an embedding is a layer that
Has the computational speed of an array lookup and the same
Gradients as a matrix multiplication
How does it do that well just internally it uses an index lookup to actually grab the values
and it also knows what the gradient of a
matrix multiplication by our one hot encoded vector is or matrix is
Without having to go to all this trouble
And so an embedding is a matrix multiplication
With a one hot encoded vector where you never actually have to create the 100 CO detector. You just need the indexes
This is important to remember because a lot of people have heard about embeddings and they think there's something
Special and magical and
and they're absolutely not you can do exactly the same thing by creating a one hot encoded matrix and
Doing a matrix multiply. It is just a
computational shortcut nothing else
I often find when I talk to people about this in person. I have to tell them this six or seven times
Before they believe me
Because they think embeddings or something more clever
And they're not it's just a computational shortcut to do a matrix multiplication more quickly
with a 100 coded matrix by instead doing an array lookup
Okay, so let's try and create a collaborative milk filtering model
Torch
model or an architecture
Aurelion NN module is a class
so to use PI torch
So it's fullest you need to understand object-oriented programming because we have to create classes
There's a lot of tutorials about this so I won't go into detail about it, but I'll give you a quick overview
a class
could be something like
Fog or ResNet or circle?
and it's something that has some data attached to it and it has some functionality attached to it is a class code example, um
the data it has attached to it is a and the functionality attached to it is say and
so we can for example create an
Instance of this class an object of this type example, we pass in silver. So sil vout will now be in
EXA and where you can then say
EXA and it will call SE and it will say passing it nice to meet you. So that will be X and so it'll say
Hello
Delft on a silver nice to meet you. Here it is. Okay
so in
Python the way you create a class is to say class in its name
Then to say what is passed to it when you create that object
It's a special method called dunder init as we've briefly mentioned before in
Python there are all kinds of special
method names of that special behavior
They start with two underscores they end with two underscores and rapid onset dunder rotunda in it
all
Methods in
All regular methods instance methods in Python always get passed the actual object itself first
we normally call that self and then optionally anything else and
So you can then change the contents of the current object by just setting self dot whatever
To whatever you like go after this self dot a is now equal to Java
We call a method same thing that past self
Optionally anything you pass to it and then you can access the contents of self which you stashed away back here when we initialized it
so that's basically how
Object or you know, the basics of object-oriented programming works in pipe in Python
There's something else you can do
Create a new class
Which is you can pop something in parentheses after its name and that means we're going to use something called inheritance
And what inheritance means is I want to have all the functionality of this class
Plus I want to add some additional functionality
so module is a
PI torch us
Which fast AI has customized? Um, so it's kind of a fast AI version of a PI torch class
and
Probably in the next course, we'll see exactly how it works
And
But it looks a lot like a
X almost exactly like her just a regular Python class. We have an inert
And we can set
attributes to whatever we like and
one of the things we can use as an embedding and
So an embedding is just this class that does what I just described a it's the same as an as a linear layer
With a one hot encoded matrix, but it does it with this computational shortcut. You can say how many
In this case users are there and how many factors will they have?
Now there is one very special thing about things that inherit from module
Which is that when you call them, it will actually call a method called forward
So forward is a special PI torch method named. It's the most important PI torch method name
This is where you put the actual computation
So to
The grabbes of factors from an embedding. We just call it like a function, right? So this is going to get passed here the
User IDs and the movie IDs as two columns. So let's grab the zero index column and
grab the embeddings by passing them to user factors and
Then we'll do the same thing for the index one column
that's the movie IDs pass them to the movie vectors and then here there's our element wise multiplication and
Then some and now remember we've got another dimension. I'm the first axis is the
Mini-batch dimension where we want to sum over
The other dimension the index one dimension. So that's going to give us a dot product
or each
user
so for each rating for each user movie combination
So this is the dot product class
So
You can see if we look at one batch of our data
its sub-site of size shape 64 by 2 because there are 64 items in the mini batch and
each one has
This is the independent variables. So it's got the user ID and the movie IDE
And
Oh
- deep neural network based models for collaborative filtering work better than more traditional approaches like SVG or other matrix
Let's wait until we get there
So
Is X right so here is one user ID
movie ID combination
okay, and then
H 1 2016
There are the ratings
So now we created a dot product module from scratch so we can
instantiate it
passing in the number of users the number of movies and let's use 50 factors and
Now we can create a learner now this time we're not creating a CNN learner or a specific application learner
It's just a totally generic learner. So this is a learner that doesn't really know how to do anything clever
It just draws away the data you give it and the model you give it and since we're not using an application-specific learner
It doesn't know what loss function to use. So we'll tell it to use MSE
and fit
And that's it right so we've just fitted our own collaborative filtering model where we literally created the entire
Architecture. It's a pretty simple one from scratch
So that's pretty amazing
Now the results aren't great if you look at the movie lens data set benchmarks
Online you'll see this is not actually a great result
So one of the things we should do is take advantage of the tip
We just mentioned earlier in this lesson, which is when you're doing regression
Which we are here write the number between 1 and 5 is like a continuous value
We're trying to get as close to it as possible
We should tell
Passed AI what the range is?
That we can use Y range as before, so here's exactly the same thing. We've got a grey range we've stored it away
And then at the end we use as we discussed sigmoid Range
Passing in and look here. We pass in Starr self-taught way range that's going to pass in by default zero comma five point five
And so we can see
Yeah, not really any better
Um, it's worth a try
Normally, this is a little bit better, but it always depends on
When you run it, I just run it a second time while it's looking
Um now there is something else we can do though, which is that if we look back
At a little Excel version
The thing is here
Why you know these latent factors by these latent factors and at the mop
it's not really taking account of the fact that
this user
may just rape movies really badly in general regardless of what kind of movie they are and
this movie
might be just a great movie in general does everybody likes it regardless of what kind of stuff they like and
so it'd be nice to be able to represent this directly and we can do that using something we've already learned about which is
bias
We could have another single number for each movie which we just add and add another single number for each user
Which we just add
Right. Now we've already seen this for linear models, you know this idea that it's nice to be able to add a bias
Value, so let's do that
So that means that we're going to need another embedding for each user
Which is a size one. It's just a single number. We're going to add
so in other words
It's just an array lookup but remember to do an array lookup that we can kind of
Take a gradient of we have to say embedding. It will do the same thing for movie bias and
So then all of this
Is identical as before and we just add this one extra line, which is to add the user and movie bias values
And so let's train that see how it goes
Well, that was a shame it got worse
So we used to have
Finished here
Point at seven nine eight eight
9 so it's it's a little bit worse
Why is that well if you look only you're on it was quite better at was point eight six
So it's it's overfitting
Very quickly
And so what we need to do is we need to find a way
That we can train more epochs
without
Overfitting now. We've already learned about data augmentation, but like rotating images and changing their brightness and color and stuff
But it's not obvious how we would do data augmentation total laboratory filtering
And so how are we going to make it so that we can train lots of epochs without overfitting?
And to do that we're going to have to use them in court regularization and regularization is a set of techniques
Which basically allow us to use?
Models with lots of parameters and train them for a long period of time
But analyze them effectively for overfitting
Or in some way cause them to try to stop overfitting and so that is what we will look at
next week
Okay. Well, thanks everybody. So there's a lot to take in there
So, please remember to practice to experiment but listen to the lessons again
because you know for the next couple of lessons things are going to
Really quickly build on top of all the stuff that we've learnt
So please be as comfortable as it with it as you can
feel free to go back and reel it in and
Go through and and follow through the notebooks and then try to recreate as much of them yourself
Thanks everybody and I will see you next week or see you in the next lesson whenever you watch it